to answer certain questions we need to
think about the big picture what it all
means and to really evaluate those kinds
of questions the kind of you Nissa tea
that brings value to life to bring value
to this world we sometimes need to
really look at the very big picture
astronomy can sometimes give us some
perspective how unique is this world to
give you a sense of it imagine you had a
little bit of talcum powder in your
hands and you're looking at it and
you're seeing the very smallest grain
you pick one you paint it red and we're
gonna now do one of those little
contests where you're like there's a jar
and you're trying to figure out how many
marbles are in the jar so we're gonna
basically look at different size piles
and try to figure out just how unique is
this world so imagine this entire room
was filled with talcum powder and we had
one little grain of red in that one
little grain compared to an entire room
this entire space solid full is that how
unique life on Earth is nope it's bigger
than that imagine you're looking at a
mountain an enormous mountain you're
standing at the base and you're looking
way up and you're basically saying
there's this huge huge huge pile and
only one single grain represents this
planet it's a life that we know amongst
all of that is that how unique life on
Earth is nope it's even bigger imagine
you're standing at the top of the
mountain you're looking out over this
this ocean of mountains you're up in an
aircraft you're looking out over the
entire earth in this entire earth the
land the Seas everything we know the
entire planets taken as one huge
enormous ball of talcum powder floating
in space
with one little red grains buried
somewhere in the middle of that what is
the chance that if you were to just pick
up one single grain that it would be the
red one just think of how improbable
that is we are one world out of seven
hundred billion billion stars to really
appreciate what it means for the you
Nissa tea of life on earth so far as we
know this is it right that the life that
we experience on this planet the thing
we take for granted every single day of
our lives is so astoundingly miraculous
that even to use the word miracle
doesn't come anywhere close to how
incredibly unique this world is how
incredibly special life is consider for
a moment that the most miraculous thing
you could possibly imagine the most
amazing synchronistic experience
multiply that by a hundred and imagine
that happening everywhere in the world
simultaneously like so much so that the
miraculous becomes ordinary and then
what in that context would be miraculous
well now we're just beginning to get
there we would need to do that three or
four more times to get to the level of
improbability that life is on this
planet okay and I'm only saying this
because I'm trying to give you a real
sense as to just how important it is
just how meaningful our lives are just
how special this world is compared to an
entire universe that for all that we
know may be empty so in that particular
sense I invite you to understand I
invite you to think about your lives as
being more special into greater scheme
of things than you may have appreciated
then in a sense that we are in a
position of having an influence over our
evolution being able to make choices
that define the future of this plan
we have drew genetic evolution and
manipulation of Technology the capacity
to create machines that may someday be
even more Makaveli and than ourselves it
only takes one right and that in effect
there are these risks that we have in a
sense gotten into because of business or
because of the way in which we organize
ourselves in the world the ways that we
think about community and so on that we
completely overlook that there is in a
sense a greater scheme that we need to
in a sense answer back to to really
appreciate just how incredible and
unique just how special it is that the
choices that we make need to in a sense
respond to the greater scheme of just
how special this is
we think of ourselves as a species you
know a species that has an effect taken
over the entire planet and that we are
in a position to be making choices about
ecosystems and what happens with
resources and things like that and then
in effect we think about it in terms of
our own lives but we are even in
comparison to other animals so much more
similar to them than we are different
from Iraq right the real comparison is
an absolute scale not a relative one so
I invite you to appreciate the
specialness of just how unique this
world is we go to beautiful places and
then we come back and we say well geez
you know I'm living in an ordinary town
and so on and so forth there's no such
place on this entire planet that is
ordinary when you think of all of those
other places you could be in the
universe to actually be here in this
paradise so when we're thinking about
risk an existential risk and our role
and our choices that we make we have to
consider that the way in which our minds
work to some extent is like a fish in
water we don't perceive the biases we
don't perceive the ways in which our
choices actually are influenced by our
biology we need in a sense a deeper set
of tools to make the kinds of choices
govern things like if we are going to be
in possession of evolution if we are in
a sense going to be influencing the
course of the future of this planet
appropriate use of technology
appropriate use of of how we relate to
one another appropriate use of power we
need a deeper level of tools we need a
deeper level of decision-making science
and technology although they can show us
how something can be done they do not
give us the tools to know what should be
done
there's no OTT in science or technology
there's no particular reason why we
should die to build something or not
build something they'll tell us how but
they don't say anything about what it
means what is what is the connection
that that crate how does that make life
more meaningful or not our economic
system is in effect at this particular
point have become kind of a prison the
more in which we we are looking at
creating value or having things for a
purpose we have lost the message the
idea that meaningfulness is deeper than
value or purpose that the thing that is
ultimately the case is that life is
inherently meaningful I sometimes get
asked what is the meaning of life and I
can only reply there's no real
difference that every life is meaningful
and everything that is meaningful is
alive and that any notion of value or
purpose has to emerge from that that we
can't have value or purpose without
already having some sort of connections
some sort of in-between this because
none of us owns the English language
none of us owns any particular word we
basically share the sensitive
meaningfulness and the capacity to
communicate is in effect a shared thing
it is an in-between this is an
interpersonal aspect so when we're
thinking about how do we make good
choices how do we enter into the kind of
stewardship that recognizes the true
meaningfulness the true value of life on
this earth how do we begin to think
about those choices in an effective way
in a way that in a sense is responding
to the sheer meaningfulness the sheer
depth of what is when I was 16 I made a
commitment my commitment was that I was
going to encounter nature in a
completely non projecting way and of
completely I'm going to accept it as it
is I'm going to encounter it without
trying to have it translate itself into
my language to try to codify it in any
specific mathematics or in any
particular modality that I in a sense
would be naked in front of it that I
would go 100 percent of the distance to
learn what was and is and out of that
came this this constellation of ideas
this constellation of thoughts these
experiences that led me to certain
insights and while it might take a while
to describe what those insights are and
it's not really relevant at this very
moment those insights led to to a series
of ideas about ethics it was actually
unexpected for me I wasn't really
thinking that I would end up with a
theory of ethics it kind of happened by
accident but I'm beginning to see that
that's probably the most important thing
the most useful thing that could
possibly have happened if we're going to
make good choices as a species we need a
deeper set of tools we need a kind of
philosophy of choice we're taught in
schools that philosophy is mostly
useless I'll tell you as a business
person philosophy is like the keystone
they've made it possible for business to
actually work why are we even in
business why are we even doing any of
the things that we do well somewhere a
level at some level or another it's
gonna come back to the notion of
meaningfulness what matters to you what
matters in this situation what matters
in life itself
because at the end of the day that's all
there is
out of this core came two ideas about
ethics one of them is a symmetry ethics
most of you are for sure familiar with
this do unto others as you'd have them
do it to yourself the notion of equality
the notion of fairness
all of those are symmetry concepts the
piece that seemed to be missing was the
notion of continuity ethics the kind of
thing that governs Continuum's of flow
cycles that actually connect back to
themselves the notion of continuity and
innocence the the kind of connectedness
the flow that occurs between people
having a certain smoothness smoothness a
consistent rate of change turns out to
be just as important to theory of ethics
as anything else that I can think of
they it balances to symmetry ethics and
these may be very abstract ideas but it
turns out that one layer past that comes
some fairly concrete things when we want
to recognize what is a good choice to
some extent we have to have an idea of
what goodness means in that context what
does it mean to make a good choice what
is what is a way in which we become the
people become the person that can
recognize when we have made a good
choice how would we know what does it
mean to do that it's a choice that in
effect is Omni considerate it not only
manifests in the moment but it opens the
door for potentials in the future it is
in a sense of choice which considers not
just what you think but also what you
feel in your heart and not just your
heart but the heart of the person that
you're talking to the heart of the
community that you're in the deep
meaning of what it is to be alive and to
be able to respond from that place that
deep place of loving what is loving life
itself in the most profound way possible
including not just yourself but in your
community but the entire planet in which
we live now that is a good choice
wouldn't it be good news if it was
always possible to make an omni consider
a choice to make a win-win choice I'm
here to tell you it is there is no
circumstance there is no such thing as a
circumstance that is constructed that is
actually in life I should distinguish
between constructive circumstances where
somebody's creating some hypothesis you
can always create a hypothesis that
assumes the conclusion is trying to
reach if you're constructing an ethical
hypothesis yeah there's lots of
impossible situations but if you're
talking about actual life being here now
and making choices as a person in the
moment it's always possible to make a
win-win choice categorically always
possible Point Blank period that's a
pretty strong statement I'm willing to
back it up the next thing that is
actually surprising that's kind of
important is that these choices these
win-win choices let's say you were in a
situation and you made a win-win choice
you actually figured out a way to make
an Omni considerate choice it was worth
the time it's always worth the time to
search for the win-win choice right it's
always worth it because we know it
exists in each situation to the best of
our capacity we search for the win-win
choice but let's say that the effortless
the extreme process the extreme process
that we may need to go through to find
what that choice is doesn't make it any
easier to make the next win-win choice
in the situation and immediately
subsequently follows right that would be
kind of a bummer but it turns out again
derived from a theory of ethics which
itself is derived from a foundation that
is even deeper than physics because it
would have to be because physics can't
tell you what to do so you need to sense
a deeper theory you need something that
comes out of measurement itself
something that comes out of the literal
foundations of what it means to do
science or mathematics at all that out
of that rich context that first person
direct encounter context it's possible
to know that the choices that are
win-win are actually contiguous with one
another then in a hyperspace of all
possible choices
that there is an effect a sequence that
the capacity to make a win-win choice
makes it actually easier to make the
subsequent win-win choice in a situation
that immediately follows many of you
have probably been told that if you tell
the truth it gets easier to continue
telling the truth that you know if you
lie you have to start building up more
and more hypotheses to to sort of
protect that and that if you just tell
the truth in the first place then what
effectively happens is is that it just
flows so the second idea beyond just
that it's always possible to make a
win-win choice is it these notions of
win-win choice are actually contiguous
with one another that it makes it easier
to make the win-win choice once you get
to the point that you're synchronized
with that life flows in an omni
considerate way that's really really
good news because there's no prior
reason for us to assume that that would
be the case
the third thing which is pretty
important to know as far as making
effective choices individually as
community as a world given the huge
development of exponential technology
you know we have devices that at this
particular point that I have become
aware could end all life on this planet
in a millisecond that even there are
things happening in the world that there
is a very small risk that I wouldn't
even finish this sentence and all this
would disappear I'm not here to go into
those particular topics I'm actually
here to talk about the good things but
good possibilities so we know that we
can make win-win choices we know that we
have the capacity to once we've made
win-win choices that it will continue to
do so
the third thing that's important to know
is that the degree to which it seems
that we cannot make a win-win choice in
any given situation is proportional to
the degree to which we need to upgrade
our capacity to imagine in other words
that in a hyper space of all possible
choices we can make that there is a
gradient that allows us to essentially
seek the direction whatever it is that
you can imagine which is the closest
thomna considerate
the closest to a true win-win choice is
the vector direction that you need to
keep going in to converge on the path of
right action that's actually also very
fortunate because it means that we now
have not only a capacity to know that
it's worth searching for a win-win
choice and that it's viable to do so and
to continue to do so it is also viable
to use your current position to navigate
to the position at which the path of
right action for you as an individual in
your capacity to make choice to in a
sense be a representative of
consciousness in this entire universe
now that's pretty special that's
actually as profound a good news as it's
possible to have which is why I chose
that as this particular topic although
there are thousands of other things that
we could talk about that would be fun
and amusing and worthwhile I invite you
to treat your choice your capacity to
choose as sacred in the same way that I
would describe this world as being
critically sacred the notion of sacred
is is a is a deepening of the notion of
value a deepening of the notion of
purpose a deepening of the notion of
meaningfulness how far down can we go
with that how deep and rich can it
become that's what I invite you into to
think about your choice as connected to
that deep essence of what is and insofar
as you honor that in yourself life will
become richer more alive people become
healthier and more integrated
communities become more fun and
healthier and the thriving of this world
becomes something which is absolute love
is that which enables choice
love is always stronger than fear always
choose on the basis of love namaste
[Applause]